I think we should be a bit more willing, perhaps, to look at the beautiful sight of the sunlight bursting out from behind the clouds and go, "Wait a minute, that's two cats dancing the salsa!" (Laughter) (Applause) Or seeing the big, white, puffy one up there over the shopping center looks like the Abominable Snowman going to rob a bank. (Laughter) They're like nature's version of those inkblot images, you know, that shrinks used to show their patients in the '60s, and I think if you consider the shapes you see in the clouds, you'll save money on psychoanalysis bills. Let's say you're in love. All right? And you look up and what do you see? Right? Or maybe the opposite. You've just been dumped by your partner, and everywhere you look, it's kissing couples. (Laughter) Perhaps you're having a moment of existential angst. You know, you're thinking about your own mortality. And there, on the horizon, it's the Grim Reaper. (Laughter) Or maybe you see a topless sunbather. What would that mean? What would that mean? I have no idea. But one thing I do know is this: The bad press that clouds get is totally unfair. I think we should stand up for them, which is why, a few years ago, I started the Cloud Appreciation Society. Tens of thousands of members now in almost 100 countries around the world. And all these photographs that I'm showing, they were sent in by members. And the society exists to remind people of this: Clouds are not something to moan about. Far from it. They are, in fact, the most diverse, evocative, poetic aspect of nature. I think, if you live with your head in the clouds every now and then, it helps you keep your feet on the ground. And I want to show you why, with the help of some of my favorite types of clouds. Let's start with this one. It's the cirrus cloud, named after the Latin for a lock of hair. It's composed entirely of ice crystals cascading from the upper reaches of the troposphere, and as these ice crystals fall, they pass through different layers with different winds and they speed up and slow down, giving the cloud these brush-stroked appearances, these brush-stroke forms known as fall streaks. And these winds up there can be very, very fierce. They can be 200 miles an hour, 300 miles an hour. These clouds are bombing along, but from all the way down here, they appear to be moving gracefully, slowly, like most clouds. And so to tune into the clouds is to slow down, to calm down. It's like a bit of everyday meditation. Those are common clouds. What about rarer ones, like the lenticularis, the UFO-shaped lenticularis cloud? These clouds form in the region of mountains. When the wind passes, rises to pass over the mountain, it can take on a wave-like path in the lee of the peak, with these clouds hovering at the crest of these invisible standing waves of air, these flying saucer-like forms, and some of the early black-and-white UFO photos are in fact lenticularis clouds. It's true. A little rarer are the fallstreak holes. All right? This is when a layer is made up of very, very cold water droplets, and in one region they start to freeze, and this freezing sets off a chain reaction which spreads outwards with the ice crystals cascading and falling down below, giving the appearance of jellyfish tendrils down below. Rarer still, the Kelvin–Helmholtz cloud. Not a very snappy name. Needs a rebrand. This looks like a series of breaking waves, and it's caused by shearing winds -- the wind above the cloud layer and below the cloud layer differ significantly, and in the middle, in between, you get this undulating of the air, and if the difference in those speeds is just right, the tops of the undulations curl over in these beautiful breaking wave-like vortices. All right. Those are rarer clouds than the cirrus, but they're not that rare. If you look up, and you pay attention to the sky, you'll see them sooner or later, maybe not quite as dramatic as these, but you'll see them. And you'll see them around where you live. Clouds are the most egalitarian of nature's displays, because we all have a good, fantastic view of the sky. And these clouds, these rarer clouds, remind us that the exotic can be found in the everyday. Nothing is more nourishing, more stimulating to an active, inquiring mind than being surprised, being amazed. It's why we're all here at TED, right? But you don't need to rush off away from the familiar, across the world to be surprised. You just need to step outside, pay attention to what's so commonplace, so everyday, so mundane that everybody else misses it. One cloud that people rarely miss is this one: the cumulonimbus storm cloud. It's what's produces thunder and lightning and hail. These clouds spread out at the top in this enormous anvil fashion stretching 10 miles up into the atmosphere. They are an expression of the majestic architecture of our atmosphere. But from down below, they are the embodiment of the powerful, elemental force and power that drives our atmosphere. To be there is to be connected in the driving rain and the hail, to feel connected to our atmosphere. It's to be reminded that we are creatures that inhabit this ocean of air. We don't live beneath the sky. We live within it. And that connection, that visceral connection to our atmosphere feels to me like an antidote. It's an antidote to the growing tendency we have to feel that we can really ever experience life by watching it on a computer screen, you know, when we're in a wi-fi zone. But the one cloud that best expresses why cloudspotting is more valuable today than ever is this one, the cumulus cloud. Right? It forms on a sunny day. If you close your eyes and think of a cloud, it's probably one of these that comes to mind. All those cloud shapes at the beginning, those were cumulus clouds. The sharp, crisp outlines of this formation make it the best one for finding shapes in. And it reminds us of the aimless nature of cloudspotting, what an aimless activity it is. You're not going to change the world by lying on your back and gazing up at the sky, are you? It's pointless. It's a pointless activity, which is precisely why it's so important. The digital world conspires to make us feel eternally busy, perpetually busy. You know, when you're not dealing with the traditional pressures of earning a living and putting food on the table, raising a family, writing thank you letters, you have to now contend with answering a mountain of unanswered emails, updating a Facebook page, feeding your Twitter feed. And cloudspotting legitimizes doing nothing. (Laughter) And sometimes we need — (Applause) Sometimes we need excuses to do nothing. We need to be reminded by these patron goddesses of idle fellows that slowing down and being in the present, not thinking about what you've got to do and what you should have done, but just being here, letting your imagination lift from the everyday concerns down here and just being in the present, it's good for you, and it's good for the way you feel. It's good for your ideas. It's good for your creativity. It's good for your soul. So keep looking up, marvel at the ephemeral beauty, and always remember to live life with your head in the clouds. Thank you very much. (Applause)
Creo que deberíamos estar más dispuestos, tal vez, a mirar el hermoso espectáculo de la luz del Sol estallando detrás de las nubes y pensar, "Espera un minuto, ¡son dos gatos bailando salsa!" (Risas) (Aplausos) O ver esta nube grande, blanca y esponjosa sobre el centro comercial que parece el abominable hombre de las nieves que va a robar un banco. (Risas) Son como la versión de la naturaleza de esas manchas de tinta, que los psicólogos les mostraban a sus pacientes en los años 60, y creo que si tienen en cuenta las formas que ven en las nubes, ahorrarán dinero en las facturas del psicoanálisis. Supongamos que están enamorados. Miran hacia arriba y ¿qué ven? ¿Cierto? O tal vez lo contrario. Los acaba de dejar su pareja, y dondequiera que miran, ven parejas besándose. (Risas) Tal vez están pasando por un momento de angustia existencial. Ya saben, están pensando en su propia muerte. Y allí, en el horizonte, está la Parca. (Risas) O tal vez vean una bañista en topless. ¿Qué significa esto? ¿Qué significa esto? No tengo ni idea. Pero lo que sí sé es esto: La mala fama que tienen las nubes es totalmente injusta. Creo que deberíamos defenderlas, razón por la que, hace unos años fundé la Cloud Appreciation Society. Ya cuenta con decenas de miles de miembros en casi 100 países del mundo. Y todas estas fotografías que estoy mostrando han sido enviadas por ellos. Y esta sociedad existe para recordarle a la gente esto: Las nubes no son algo de lo que quejarse. Al contrario. Son, de hecho, el aspecto más variado, evocador y poético de la naturaleza. Creo que vivir con la cabeza en las nubes de vez en cuando, ayuda a mantener los pies en el suelo. Y quiero mostrarles el por qué, con la ayuda de algunos de mis tipos favoritos de nubes. Vamos a empezar con este. Es un cirro, nombre que viene de la palabra latina para designar un mechón de pelo. Se compone en su totalidad de cristales de hielo cayendo en cascada desde la parte superior de la troposfera. Conforme estos cristales de hielo caen, pasan a través de diferentes capas con diferentes vientos que los aceleran y frenan, dándole a la nube esta apariencia de cepillado, estas formas de pinceladas conocidas como mechones caídos. Y estos vientos allá arriba pueden ser muy feroces. Pueden ser de entre 300 y 500 km por hora. Estas nubes van muy rápido, pero desde aquí abajo parecen moverse con gracia, lentamente, como casi todas las nubes. Así que para sintonizarse con las nubes hay que ir despacio, calmarse. Es como un poco de meditación diaria. Estas son nubes comunes. ¿Qué pasa con las más raras, como las lenticulares, las nubes lenticulares con forma de ovni? Estas nubes se forman en regiones montañosas. Cuando hay viento, este se eleva para sobrepasar la montaña, y puede ondularse en la curva del pico, con estas nubes flotando en la cima de estas ondas de aire estacionarias e invisibles, estas formas como de platillo volador, y algunas de las primeras fotos en blanco y negro de ovnis, son de hecho nubes lenticulares. Es cierto. Un poco más raras son los nubes agujero. Las vemos cuando una capa de gotas de agua muy, muy frías empiezan a congelarse en una región, y esta congelación pone en marcha una reacción en cadena que se extiende hacia el exterior con los cristales de hielo cayendo en cascada, dando la apariencia de tentáculos de medusa. Más rara aún es la nube Kelvin-Helmholtz. No es un nombre muy elegante. Necesita que se lo cambien. Esta nube parece una sucesión de olas rompiéndose, y esto es causado por vientos de corte: los vientos por encima y por debajo de la capa de nubes difieren significativamente, y en el centro, en medio, se consigue esta ondulación del aire, y si la diferencia de velocidades es la adecuada, la parte superior de los rizos se ondula en estos hermosos vórtices ondulatorios. Son nubes más inusuales que el cirro, pero no son tan inusuales. Si alzan su mirada y prestan atención al cielo, las verán tarde o temprano, tal vez no vean nubes tan impresionantes como estas, pero las verán. Y las verán en la zona donde viven. Las nubes son el espectáculo más igualitario de la naturaleza, porque todos tenemos una fantástica vista del cielo. Y estas nubes, las más inusuales, nos recuerdan que lo exótico puede encontrarse en lo cotidiano. No hay nada más revitalizante, más estimulante para una mente activa y curiosa, que ser sorprendida, ser maravillada. Por eso estamos todos aquí, en TED, ¿cierto? Pero no tienen que precipitarse lejos de lo familiar, al otro lado del mundo, para ser sorprendidos. Solo tienen que salir, prestar atención a lo que es tan común, tan cotidiano, tan mundano, que el resto del mundo lo pasa por alto. Una nube que la gente rara vez echa de menos es esta: la nube de tormenta cumulonimbo. Es la que produce truenos, rayos y granizo. Estas nubes se extienden sobre esta enorme forma de yunque, desplegándose 16 km hacia arriba en la atmósfera. Son una expresión de la majestuosa arquitectura de nuestra atmósfera. Pero desde abajo, son la encarnación de la fuerza poderosa y elemental que impulsa nuestra atmósfera. Estar ahí es estar conectado con la lluvia y el granizo, sentirse conectado a nuestra atmósfera. Hay que recordar que somos criaturas que habitan en este océano de aire. No vivimos bajo el cielo. Vivimos dentro de él. Y esa conexión visceral con nuestra atmósfera me parece un antídoto. Un antídoto a la creciente tendencia que tenemos de sentir que realmente podemos experimentar la vida viéndola en una pantalla de computadora, cuando estamos en una zona wi-fi. Pero las nubes que mejor expresan por qué hoy es más importante que nunca observarlas son estas, los cúmulos. ¿Verdad? Se forman en los días soleados. Si cierran los ojos y piensan en una nube, probablemente sea una de estas la que viene a la mente. Todas las formas de nubes del comienzo eran cúmulos. Sus contornos nítidos y definidos las hace las mejores para encontrar formas en ellas. Y nos recuerda lo intrascendente que es observar nubes, la actividad tan anodina que es. No van a cambiar el mundo tendiéndose boca arriba y mirando hacia el cielo. Es inútil. Es una actividad inútil, y por eso, precisamente, que es tan importante. El mundo digital conspira para hacernos sentir eternamente ocupados, permanentemente ocupados. Ya saben, cuando no están lidiando con las presiones cotidianas de ganarse la vida y llevar comida a la mesa, formar una familia, escribir cartas de agradecimiento, tienen que lidiar ahora con una montaña de correos electrónicos para responder, poner al día una página de Facebook, actualizar su Twitter. Y el observar las nubes legitima el no hacer nada. (Risas) Y a veces necesitamos... (Aplausos) A veces necesitamos excusas para no hacer nada. Estas diosas patronas de los ociosos nos tienen que recordar que es bueno bajar el ritmo y vivir el presente, no pensando en lo que hay que hacer y lo que ya debería estar hecho, sino tan solo en estar aquí, dejando que la imaginación se aleje de las preocupaciones cotidianas de aquí abajo y solo vivir el presente, porque es bueno para uno y es bueno para el modo en que uno se siente. Es bueno para las ideas. Es bueno para la creatividad. Es bueno para el alma. Así que sigan alzando su mirada, admirando la belleza efímera, y recuerden siempre vivir con la cabeza en las nubes. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)